start with a triangular array of
triangles with n triangles on the base
imagine placing one token in the first
triangle for one squared tokens
then place two tokens in each of the
triangles in the second diagonal adding
two squared tokens
place three tokens on each of the three
triangles in the third diagonal adding
three squared total tokens and continue
this process
so that the n minus 1 tokens in each of
the n minus 1 triangles in the next to
last diagonal add n minus 1 squared
tokens
and the n tokens in each of the n
triangles in the last diagonal add n
squared tokens
so the total number of tokens is the sum
of the first n squares
now create a copy of the diagram
and rotate it 120 degrees
[Music]
then
create a copy from this one and rotate
it another 120 degrees resulting in
three total copies
notice that at any position if you add
the number of tokens at that position
over the three copies you always get two
n plus one
thus when we stack all three copies
together we have a triangular array of
stacks of tokens with two n plus one
tokens so the total number of tokens is
two n plus one
times
the nth triangular number
but this is equal to two n plus one
times n times n plus one over two
consequently
three
multiplied by the sum of the first n
squares
is equal to two n plus one times n
times n plus one over two
dividing both sides by three
gives the formula for the sum of the
first n squares to be equal to two n
plus one times n times n plus one over
six
[Music]
you